Simon Fraser University Staff Association fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Simon Fraser University Staff Association fonds
1966 - 1974
F-119
Q106643003
50 cm of textual records 11 photographs
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
PHYSICAL DESCRIPTION: 11 photographs located in F-119-3-0-0-7
Simon Fraser University Staff Association
The Simon Fraser University Staff Association was established in 1966 by staff on campus who felt that conditions and salaries at the university were in need of improvement. An association, rather than a union, was formed as staff felt that freedom of action within the university was preferable at the time. By 1968 the Staff Association was an officially recognized body of the university, and was registered under the Societies Act. The aims of the Staff Association, as given in its 1968 constitution, were to unite staff under a single organization capable of acting on its behalf, to communicate with administration on matters affecting staff, to obtain and improve the best possible conditions of employment, to have representation on university committees, and to encourage the continued education of its members. In 1971, the constitution was changed to read:
The primary object of the Association is to serve the common interests of the non-academic employees of Simon Fraser University who are not members of trade unions in all matters concerning wages, salaries, benefits, and conditions of employment in such manner as to promote the fair treatment of all such employees individually and as compared in general to other persons and groups of persons similarly employed at Simon Fraser University and in other parts of the Greater Vancouver area.
Membership in the Association was voluntary, although all eligible staff were encouraged to join in order to give it stronger support for voicing the opinions and needs of its members.
By 1974, some members of the university staff expressed interest in union representation. A Committee to Investigate Alternatives was formed to explore the possibilities of union representation, although the Staff Association executive did not support this group. Concurrently, a number of unions attempted to organize staff on campus: the Canadian Union of Public Employees, the Office and Technical Employees Union, and the Association of University and College Employees all campaigned to represent staff at SFU. In response the Staff Association decided to seek certification through the Labour Relations Board. On November 19, 1974 an election was held to determine if staff at SFU wanted a union, and if so, which union they wanted to represent them (the Staff Association or the Association of University and College Employees). Staff voted to have AUCE as their representative, and, as a result, the Staff Association began winding up its affairs. By December 1974 it had moved out of its offices, gave their surplus equipment and stationary to AUCE, and turned their records over to the university archives.
published
Full
Revised
The title of the fonds is based on the name of the creating body.
Fonds consists of records created, received, and collected by the Simon Fraser University Staff Association in carrying out its functional activities. Records reflect its constitution, executive and general meetings, social activities, benefits, newsletter, unionization and records of the membership chairman. Records include those collected from outside the fonds by a former archivist and those donated from other sources. Includes file lists, correspondence, memoranda, agenda, minutes, financial records, newsletter, bulletins, membership lists, posters, and a staff handbook.
The materials were retained in original order where possible. A Staff Association file list is available in the records (file 119-1-0-1), which shows how files were ordered in the office of origin. This arrangement was maintained in the series "Staff Association Office files." The archivist arranged files in the remaining series. Files in the series, "Collected files" did not originate with the Staff Association, but were collected by a previous archivist, or were donated from other unknown sources.
Photographic materials; Textual records; Labour
The Staff Association donated the fonds to the archives after its dissolution. A former archivist collected other records and some were donated from other unknown sources.
All accessions have been processed as of February 2006. No further accruals are expected.
Please consult the inventory of the Association of University and College Employees Local #2 fonds, F-120.
Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as stipulated by Archives policy or the donor. Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
Series descriptions and file lists are available.
- Staff Association office files, 1966 - 1974; F-119-1; 36 cm of textual records
  published
  Series consists of records created, received and collected by the Simon Fraser University Staff Association in carrying out its functional activities. Records reflect the Association's efforts to represent staff and advocate on their behalf. Also reflects communication with administration, involvement in university life, staff education, social and recreational activities, and the drive to achieve union certification. Includes file lists, constitution, correspondence, memoranda, financial records, agenda, newsletters, minutes of executive and general meetings, staff handbook, and salary proposals.
  - Filing lists, 1971; F-119-1-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 119-1)
    Textual records
    Pending review
  - Annual meetings minutes and notices, 1969 - 1972; F-119-1-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 119-1)
  - Annual salary review, 1967 - 1973; F-119-1-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 119-1)
  - Berger report - "Legal Position of the SFU Staff Association", 1968; F-119-1-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 119-1)
  - Bursary, 1970 - 1972; F-119-1-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 119-1)
    Restricted in whole
  - Charter flights, 1970 - 1973; F-119-1-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 119-1)
  - Communications media, 1973; F-119-1-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 119-1)
  - Constitution and extraordinary resolutions, 1966 - 1972; F-119-1-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 119-1)
  - Constitution, 1966 - 1969; F-119-1-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 119-1)
  - Constitution, 1966 - 1974; F-119-1-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 119-1)
  - Dances, 1969 - 1972; F-119-1-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 119-1)
  - Dental plans, 1971 - 1972; F-119-1-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 119-1)
  - Do You Know and Special bulletins, 1972 - 1974; F-119-1-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 119-1)
  - Dogs on Campus, 1973; F-119-1-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 119-1)
  - Education Committee, 1968 - 1973; F-119-1-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 119-1)
  - Employee grievance procedures, 1971; F-119-1-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 119-1)
  - Executive Committee meetings, 1967; F-119-1-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 119-1)
  - Executive Committee meetings, 1968; F-119-1-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 119-1)
  - Executive Committee meetings, 1969 - 1970; F-119-1-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 119-1)
  - Executive Committee meetings, 1972 - 1974; F-119-1-0-0-20 (Archival box - standard 119-1)
  - Executive Meetings, 1974; F-119-1-0-0-21 (Archival box - standard 119-2)
  - Faculty Association, 1968 - 1971; F-119-1-0-0-22 (Archival box - standard 119-2)
  - General Meetings, 1966; F-119-1-0-0-23 (Archival box - standard 119-2)
  - General Meetings, 1967; F-119-1-0-0-24 (Archival box - standard 119-2)
  - General Meetings, 1968; F-119-1-0-0-25 (Archival box - standard 119-2)
  - General Meetings - minutes and notices, 1969; F-119-1-0-0-26 (Archival box - standard 119-2)
  - General Meetings - minutes and notices, 1970; F-119-1-0-0-27 (Archival box - standard 119-2)
  - General Meetings - minutes and notices, 1971; F-119-1-0-0-28 (Archival box - standard 119-2)
  - General Meetings - minutes and notices, 1972; F-119-1-0-0-29 (Archival box - standard 119-2)
  - General Meetings - minutes and notices, 1973; F-119-1-0-0-30 (Archival box - standard 119-2)
  - General Meetings - minutes and notices, 1974; F-119-1-0-0-31 (Archival box - standard 119-2)
  - Handbook, 1968 - 1972; F-119-1-0-0-32 (Archival box - standard 119-2)
  - Job redundancy and security, 1968 - 1972; F-119-1-0-0-33 (Archival box - standard 119-2)
  - Medical Benefits, 1966 - 1973; F-119-1-0-0-34 (Archival box - standard 119-2)
  - Modified work week, 1972 - 1974; F-119-1-0-0-35 (Archival box - standard 119-2)
  - Registrar of Companies, 1967 - 1972; F-119-1-0-0-36 (Archival box - standard 119-2)
  - Salaries and Conditions Committee - minutes, 1967 - 1970; F-119-1-0-0-37 (Archival box - standard 119-2)
  - Salaries, 1967 - 1969; F-119-1-0-0-38 (Archival box - standard 119-3)
  - Salaries, 1968 - 1969; F-119-1-0-0-39 (Archival box - standard 119-3)
  - SCAN, 1967 - 1968; F-119-1-0-0-40 (Archival box - standard 119-3)
  - SCAN, 1968 - 1970; F-119-1-0-0-41 (Archival box - standard 119-3)
  - SCAN, 1971 - 1973; F-119-1-0-0-42 (Archival box - standard 119-3)
  - Staff representation on University Committee, 1967 - 1969; F-119-1-0-0-43 (Archival box - standard 119-3)
  - Suggestion Award Plan, 1974; F-119-1-0-0-44 (Archival box - standard 119-3)
  - Unionization / certification correspondence 1/2, 1967 - 1974; F-119-1-0-0-45 (Archival box - standard 119-3)
    Restricted in part
  - Unionization / certification correspondence 2/2, 1967 - 1974; F-119-1-0-0-46 (Archival box - standard 119-3)
    Open
  - University Centre Building, 1966; F-119-1-0-0-47 (Archival box - standard 119-3)
  - Welfare committee, [ca 1970] - [ca 1974]; F-119-1-0-0-48 (Archival box - standard 119-3)
- Membership Chairman's files, 1968 - 1974; F-119-2; 6 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to membership in the Simon Fraser University Staff Association. Records reflect membership solicitations, remittance, and resignations. Includes membership lists, correspondence, and memoranda.
  - Membership Chairman - memberships remittance lists, 1968 - 1974; F-119-2-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 119-4)
  - Membership Chairman - membership solicitations, 1971 - 1973; F-119-2-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 119-4)
  - Membership Chairman - resignations, 1971 - 1974; F-119-2-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 119-4)
  - Membership Chairman - correspondence, 1973 - 1974; F-119-2-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 119-4)
  - Membership Chairman - resignations past date of certification, 1974; F-119-2-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 119-4)
  - Membership Chairman - general, 1974; F-119-2-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 119-4)
- Collected files, 1968 - 1974; F-119-3; 7 cm of textual records 11 photographs; Physical description: 11 photographs located in F-119-3-0-0-7
  Series consists of records relating to the Simon Fraser University Staff Association collected by a former archivist or donated from other unknown sources. Records reflect membership, publications, and information relating to efforts to unionize staff at the university. Includes newsletter, bulletins, memoranda, correspondence, agenda, and posters.
  - Membership, 1971 - 1974; F-119-3-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 119-4)
  - Publications / Newsletters, 1968 - 1974; F-119-3-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 119-4)
  - Unionization - Committee to investigate alternatives, 1973; F-119-3-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 119-4)
  - Unionization - OTEU and CUPE organizing materials, 1973 - 1974; F-119-3-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 119-4)
  - Unionization - AUCE handouts / circulars during organization drive, 1974; F-119-3-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 119-4)
  - Union information meeting, 1974; F-119-3-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 119-4)
  - Election poster, October [19--?]; F-119-3-0-0-7
    Textual records; Photographic materials